Okay, we are going to call to order the
My name is City Council meeting regular meeting for today's date and time
I did this administer oath of office to Brian and Doug Brian not being here tonight
I know Melissa will catch him another time. Good. I'm ready here. Oh, I didn't all right
for two down to me, please. Bye. Doug question. Do you sell on my swear firm? Do you sell
my swear firm that I will support obey and defend the constitution of the United States?
I will support obey and defend the constitution of the United States and the constitution of the state of Oklahoma
and the constitution of the state of Oklahoma and then I will not knowingly receive directly or indirectly
any money or a derogable thing. We'll not knowingly receive directly or indirectly any Money or other valuable thing
for the performance or nonperformance at any act or duty pertaining to my office others in the compensation allowed by law
for the performance or nonperformance of any act or duty pertain to my office other than the compensation allowed by law
That I will safely discharge
I will safely discharge.
According to the best of my ability.
According.
Sorry.
According to the best by ability.
The duties that my office during such time and I am a member of the City Council,
work one.
The duties of my office during such time.
I remember the City Council.
Work two.
Yes.
Good.
Okay.
And the Board of Trustees of the Mayanis special utility authority of City of
the City of Mayana Obama.
And the Board of Trustees of the Mayanis city.
Our Mayanis special utility authority.
That's the City of Mayanis Obama.
Congratulations.
Thank you.
And I want to thank Doug and Brian for their continued service on the council.
It means a lot in their great council members and make important contributions.
And when you read this, all of the, when you look at this, it looks like just two paragraphs.
But it seems like it takes forever.
It does.
It's a read the thing.
Okay.
We're going to move on to item three, which is public input on this casual personal appearances.
But the council meeting is there.
Anyone on the answer?
Which is to address the council on the agenda items?
There have been nine item four is considered gender staff.
It's recommending item is five through 11 for the consent agenda.
If you take a quick look at those.
And if there are no questions or concerns about any of those.
So it doesn't take a motion to approve as recommended by staff.
There's no further discussion.
I'll make a motion.
Okay.
We'll second it.
We'll call.
Bye.
All right, so all right, item 12 is a public hearing concerning the ordinance to annex a partial
land containing 25-183 acres in the south east corner of Section 8 Township 28-23 east
Ottawa County Oklahoma Tyler.
Yes sir, this is a public hearing.
We also have Ken Williams here from Hollis, he is the attorney that helped us with our proposal.
And also helped us with as far as the annexation and the ordinance and everything so they
are very good at this with being a busy schedule and Georgian working on contracts and everything
we've had them to help us with this.
So, and this is specifically the land related to the J.M. forms of research.
Yes, sir.
This is the land that's just adjacent.
The drawing is the survey drawing is right there, so you know the current, you can see the
salmon colored building right there, it's just dry adjacent to there.
And just for the benefit of the viewers or any one of the audience in order to serve the farm with
utilities, we are required there required to be within the city limits.
Yes sir.
The easiest way for us to be to be, so any questions for Tyler or
it, I'm sorry, 10 minute again, or Mr. Williams on the resolution, or during the public hearing.
I guess this is a public hearing portion, there being that I'm going to close the public hearing
and then we're going to move on to item 13, which is the actual ordinance to annex a parcel
of land containing 25, 183 acres in the southeast quarter of Section 8, Township 28, brings
23 east, Ottawa, County, Oklahoma, which is the aforementioned property, Tyler anything to
add.
Yes, sir.
Any questions or concerns?
Do we have a motion to approve the ordinance for the annexation?
Looks to prove.
And a second?
Sorry.
We'll call please.
All right.
Lewis, I chose.
Item 14 is an emergency clause relating to the same ordinance, which would allow the
ordinance to go into effect immediately.
And the purpose of the need for immediate effect, Tyler is just pretty much so we can get
started.
Can can talk about this a little bit more because we went back and forth.
With your permission, the ordinance would go into effect within Thursday from 10 out, the
emergency clause in the back.
We would like to get started just with everything going on.
Do we have most to approve the emergency clause as recommended by staff?
I'll make that necessary.
In the second?
Second, roll call, please.
Loomets, I'd work at question.
Hi.
I'm 15, public hearing for Grace Church for 19 foot set back,
variance locating at 138 and with ease within the limits
of the city of Miami, Christy.
Hi.
So, Bill is here tonight, also with Grace Church.
You've got any questions for him.
But this is an application for our variance.
And as you can see here, what I've got up here,
this is the church that has been built right here.
That was where Grace was at our path of stalling.
The assembly was recated.
This is the fellowship hall in Jim that was there originally
in this area here.
And then this is an area that is now Grace Church that was built back
in 2015.
I believe.
In 2015, they came before us and then asked for variance
at that time for Grace Church so that they could take up
the whole space here like the church had previously.
What they're wanting to do now is ask for the same variance
for the fellowship hall in Jim so that it will
marry up to the building next to it.
And their plans are to make that one building to join them together.
So, Bill, I saw what you guys had to just script the exterior
of the fellowship and the hall of the Jim around the red thread.
So, then you're going to actually what the deal was actually even.
So, the red iron in the back part of the building that had a lower
riff line off.
And the engineers decided that if we had one steady riff line,
we wouldn't have some of the problems that maybe we had in the past.
We wouldn't have any on adding on it.
So, basically what they're going to do is extend that riff line
and the height to the back.
And there's going to be that metal is on there's now just temporary dough.
We get the building permit, dig the footings or the new red iron
going to connect to it.
And then there's going to be renovation of the Jim slash activity center.
The restrooms, they're going to, the plans are 20 by 30 safe room,
underground safe room.
And the classroom, things like that.
Because we get to lose 60,000 square feet of building.
So, can you go back to the other picture for a second?
So, is it fair to say if you just took the red roof and extended it to the extent
of the battleship hall, that's about what the roof of the new building
would apply.
And the foot print, it would be the applies that there might be one exception in this.
in this area is a drive through this won't go back
because they want the drive through
it will be access to the alley.
There will be probably a little bit of an L-shaped here
so that the traffic can still go.
Yeah, the quarter cow, you can see it on the next slide
what is talking about right here.
So this is the back of the current square church.
This is the alley as it is today
and there's that drive through that.
He's talking about.
And so the setback is from the front,
from A Street or from the alley or a combination of both.
So it says 19 feet.
Right, that's just on the back.
So when I'm assuming, when first Christian built the gene,
they got this variance from the setback on the front.
Okay.
When we built, when we built the building,
the new building, we actually just used the line
that first Christian church had that for 100 years, for there about.
So this is just for the back.
So the setback variance on the front already exists,
and we're saying, so this is just for the back of that.
Even though they did, I'm trying to make note that the setback
would be the same on the front.
You're right.
Any other questions for Phil or Christy?
Travis, have you looked at this?
Are you okay with it?
Okay.
They have the preliminary, but I want to make sure
they're actually going to be all the back property line.
Any other questions or concerns?
If not, so this is the public hearing portion, okay.
So trying to keep that straight in my head.
We're going to close the public hearing,
there's anybody else who wants to say anything,
but there's a public hearing.
Okay, we're going to close the public hearing,
and we'll take that bottom 16, which is the application
of race church for the 19-foot setback variance.
And has this been before any other boards?
Okay, because right now, word functioning is that, but we're right, okay.
So do we have a motion to approve the application
for the setback variance?
Moved to approve.
Second, second.
We'll call for this.
Question?
Hi.
Work it.
All right.
With yes, so.
Hi.
Congratulations, Phil.
It's been a long journey.
It's been you guys, I know.
We're excited to, I mean, that corner is clean,
and we're just excited to see what it looks like when you're done.
Which may be a while, I know.
But if there's another plan coming, but for this next page,
I will be really excited and it's done.
I think we have to ask it.
Thank you.
All right.
I'm 17 public hearing again on submission.
of grant applications as a United States Department of Agricultural
World Development, Community Facility to Wreck, Flone, and Grant, and has my name on it.
Yes, there are so glenda, it's here to discuss this.
Mainly, this is a formality that the USDA RCV requires, and that's why I've chosen, because it's
used to develop. It's a world community development grant, and this is our second application.
We applied for one donor and got a front and lower foot straight department. This one we're going
for the full 35 percent, which, because of our population, that's all we'll have.
And four departments are involved in this. We have the public utilities to get a mini-dark,
which they really needed this last week. Solid waste will get some loader adapters.
Cemetery is small about it, to help them, that the main thing that we're really
hit is we're going to try to get a new, all new stuff for a 911, our dispatch, and it will be chaired,
it will be the whole shabend, so to speak. So that's part of the public hearing. It is a 65, 35,
50,000 is as much as this week as we can get. So the departments have,
got with the budget committees, and their budgets, they have this many, either in capital improvement,
or in their budgets. Today, so this is a formality. It really is going to have to sign as like a way about 45
times. I think these are sticky notes in there. This is what they require us to do. It's the only
right that I know that requires the public hearing. So our 35% is represented by the 50,000. So if we
get it, we'll get another 100,000 in round numbers for a total of 150. Each department that, like the
mini-dark is a 142,000 dollars. What we wanted to do is we wanted to get the full 50. So the other three
departments didn't quite make the 50,000 to 35%. So it's kind of like he was going to buy this anyway,
so let's see if we can get some money back. That's what my job is about is I'm going to get ready to
help out, so I'm going to get far so good. Any concerns and reasons why we wouldn't move forward? I mean,
the power 50,000 is already there in the budget. And these are just something that something
over and applied could cost. 50,000 is what we don't get. The overage of that, the total amount
for it is $25,000 to $288 or we'll get 50,000 in the departments individually. $255,000 to $288,000.
And each department, let's see, dispatch will have to come up with about $8,900.
IT will come up with 784 power supply for the dispatch.
Cemetery will be 19,000, the solid waste will come up with 9, and public utilities will
come up with around the 100,000.
So these were things that were needed in our capital to improve the budget anyway, so we're
just trying to leverage that to get an extra 50 to cover the costs.
Yes, sir.
The cemetery portion will come out of the cemetery care button.
So we'll come out of the capital.
What was it that the cemetery would do you see?
I'm sorry.
They're going to get a tractor, a small converter tractor, a loader and a rake in the
farming rake.
Right now, the department's kind of have to share, and tomorrow for each other, this way,
the cemetery can use what they would, when it dries out, they don't have to wait to
go get it from another department.
They'll have to.
And the solid waste, they're going to get a dose of light, and then they'll burn something that
may, of course, the mini-direct, you'll kind of know what that is.
That's to get into those areas that we don't have alleyways.
It was very popular last week during the storm.
I said, we needed it last time.
I told you, for 9,000, the only new set-up is that the dispatch office, plus we're going to get
some cubbies for a week, the rake run, and in new chairs for them, the ever-known chairs.
I'm going for a brush.
So, will this equipment in dispatch, would that be transferable if we end up with the...
Yeah, these are my resources, but we could take what I do.
Thank you.
And where do we know if we get the grant?
Well, Melissa skips that into more.
I will immediately send it off to USDA, and then call a representative and say, it's there.
How soon is the nice start?
Okay.
Because basically, we've done everything else.
It's ready to go with the exception of the government, you six meters.
Okay.
So, we're going to close the public hearing portion of the grant process and approval for my signature on the submission documents.
Oh, make a motion.
And the second place?
Okay.
Go from.
I work it.
All right.
What's this?
I'm 19, except for a jet parking space lease agreement with Francis, EBC, LLC.
Is that your name on it?
Yes, all right.
Did you come out please?
You come out to discuss it.
And then Chris has been in contact with George Anne.
If you guys have any questions from the contracts out of it.
Okay.
So this is all brand new.
And I know if you were here last meeting we appreciate you being back and you came in anticipation of this being voted on the proof tonight
And that may happen. It may not
Pretty kind of go through the process first crystal
I guess some some of the some of the concerns and you know not sure. I guess I'll let you address his first is
Why did the city end up using Francis EVC LL city it was opposed to anybody else out there
I don't even know how your company came to our attention
So, I don't care who addresses that but
Frank Francis solar just came to the city. We didn't go out to get them they just came to us
And so your business model is you know this grant money is out there
There's just a limited time so you're just going out to perspective series and saying well if we have an opportunity here
Are you interested?
Correct. We know are the company nobody else to do with this okay if you go to any of the other companies
They're installing this kind of thing. They want the site host to share and they spend some hour
So to you're not a journey only organization right now that is offering this to the city at no cost
The least space
No cost in this that that's correct
our first
interaction was basically a letter back to them saying that we
were very interested and
We're going to find the right right you're right originally we included
My insights in with the grants that were being offered. It was part of the Volkswagen
Finds for nine missions problem that had any way to reach some million dollars
We we gathered 54 sites that we submitted as part of that process
On 20 some of them were except of the other ones were as it happens. Miami wasn't one of those
But we're still offering the same
package deal
for all the sites
Because we also can take advantage of some
tax credit
My answer
So we have investors who have but who are interested in that so that allows us to
Come up with a business model. We're in we actually supply everything
We buy the equipment we install it will operate it maintain it everything no cost no liability
No risk for the city whatsoever our idea our business model is is that the adoption of electric vehicles is going to come much faster than
anticipates right now
every year the forecasters short and that
At the time
I saw one forecast and said by 2025
30% of the new car sold will be electric vehicles.
And can you speak to the financial stability of the company?
I can.
Francis Soler is in Francis, EVC, our both polio subsidiaries
of Francis' immutable energy.
Francis, the name Francis comes from.
Francis oil and gas family.
The founder of the company is David Jankowski, the great grandson of the guy
Sam Miller, the father of the Francis oil and gas.
He's come back to Tulsa.
He wants to bolster, foster, clean energy, you know, foam,
electric vehicles, solar power, that type of thing.
And so, Chris, you might have to speak to this.
Let's say that 10 years in, despite all the financial resources,
Francis LLC is out of business.
What is this?
One of the cities I would.
Well, you stop servicing the equipment.
What are the what rights do the city have at that point?
To you go to another company or say, come polio equipment or whatever we want to say.
Is Ben on the line?
Yes.
I actually have sent Ben when I would consider the outcomes as the default.
Okay.
And let's let him answer that question.
Ben, did you hear my question?
Yes, I did.
So, the contract does have a provision that allows either side to get out of the contract
and then the event of a material breach.
And so obviously, if they're not providing what has been outlined as the basis of this agreement,
then that gives us the city, the opportunity to get out of this agreement with them.
If we exercise that option because they're in breach, are they obligated to remove all
the equipment as part of that, you know?
Well, it provides that there is a, we have to give them 10 days notice and then they have 30 days
in which to share the breach.
And if that is not the way I would interpret this, then it would be their obligation to take care
of what the policy is and if they remove property, they would have to do whatever it is and
weren't demanding at that point because they haven't been able to fix their breach.
And you feel comfortable with it, that's enforceable.
I mean, I know when you get to court, you never know for sure what's going to happen, but...
But it shouldn't be enforceable.
Yeah, I mean, I'm looking at the language now.
George A. is the one that really closely studied this contract.
I'm just looking at the language of the default provision.
And it appears to me that it's got a percentage standard contract provision.
So.
Sorry.
This site map is we just have a site map for the travel center.
We don't have one for.
We can pull it up on Google Earth and show if we would like.
But then that's on we can pull up the Google Earth one.
So.
And this may be part of what they can speak to.
This particular agreement.
This is just for the turnpark.
Yeah.
That's what that is.
There was there was some discussion about where we put the one out there directly behind the call monitor in the lot.
And that was really we really never decided.
So I mean, that's probably something we can decide to not to.
We don't agree where we want to put it at.
Or that.
I thought that was going.
The.
The partners.
Your chapter.
Yeah.
It'd be the chapters.
I'm just trying to see what mentioned.
Of course, it doesn't mention a specific location.
Yeah.
So just as for.
I'm part of it.
It's a tourism information center.
And four offices.
And.
I think I brought up on the call.
Just because I mean.
Yeah.
I don't want to.
You know, those partners.
Both.
They're not.
They want to see what they want.
Or we.
You almost want to make sure that they're in a spot where.
They're accessible.
More.
More often.
I know you said your business model.
You can't play it all.
And it's.
What did you say the closest one.
That your company has to Miami.
But you don't have anything.
But the closest.
The closest.
Chargers that are comfortable.
This are.
But your company does not have.
Those were.
Didn't.
You say hard rock.
I rock as well.
Yeah.
And.
Tesla.
Chargers.
Super.
Are there any cities around that are about.
Our size that you deal with.
We've not.
We've not installed any.
Outside.
Yes.
We have.
That.
Our goal is to have.
A hundred of them.
A hundred sites.
This year.
And have you received approval from any other.
Communities.
Our size.
Maybe that would be a fair way to ask to question.
Norman, sure, there's four or five other guys out of what the different territories.
Okay.
But I do know that most of the sure and all that they could be improved and just started
in what we're today.
Installing the infrastructure.
And that's a city building.
And I think in talking in the back a few minutes ago, the sense of urgency, this is so much
going here in town.
It's not all that you speak to the lead time.
The distinction between the two different types.
Right.
Our ability to do this at no cost and our ability to give the city almost a million dollars
for the infrastructure that will benefit everybody, for no cost and the city.
The ability to do that depends on getting this done at a timely manner, so we can take advantage
of the tax credit finance.
The tax credits are applicable to things installed in 2019, that's fine understanding.
And there's a lead time for getting the equipment.
It's not like you've got it.
Well, it was invited.
So the lead time on the ones here in town, you said it was probably six to eight.
You've been told to be that the ones here in town are going to be 50 kilowatt size.
And those are more available.
They could take a month or two to get those.
The ones that we're talking about on the turn by are going to be 200 or 400 kilowatt.
I'm not sure yet.
But those are custom made.
And we have to order those.
And those will take months.
I've been told 46 months.
And so if you got the OK, June 1.
And it takes six months.
You're pressing the calendar to get it installed by the end of the year as you're concerned.
And if it all took two months, it would be a big deal.
We don't know how long it's going to take.
Right.
So what happens if we accept this and we don't get it installed by 2019?
Nothing on us, right?
It's not good.
Yeah.
No rest, no liability, no cost.
Put the city plan.
I guess my apprehension is.
It sounds too good to be driven.
Understood.
Our motivation for doing this is that we're the only ones doing this.
We're the ones, the funder of the company is a lot.
Who has a vision to see that we're going to have a lot of electric vehicles,
or people that want those, and people are going to need someplace to charge.
Kansas City.
the city of Kansas City and utilities up there when they had and
finance the building out of a large infrastructure and they had a lot more
electric vehicles there because people, what electric vehicles, they'll see
they can charge them. I mean, I've told a lot of people about this trying to
convince them, you know, it's like vehicles are coming through. I thought of that
but I don't know where I charge it. Why wouldn't it do that? Is this tax credit money?
You mentioned the Volkswagen dealer and what John Fumeir with, I don't know
that everybody is, is this part of that settlement? The money that's
available to the tax credits? That was the grant money. That was the grant money.
The tax incentive is a separate thing that's being offered.
What got you kind of rolling on it was the grant money and then looking at the model,
you said, we want to continue on. My understanding is that initially what we were
doing this with electric co-ops in Western Oklahoma, Western Farms specifically
in their members and we had worked out a deal with some of them where we would
install this, they saw this in a great way that they could sell more electricity
and they encouraged their members to drive what up to cars, use what electricity, et cetera, et cetera.
And so they were installing charging stations that had like the co-op officers and stuff,
and so they did that. With the understanding then that there would be a payment.
And those payments became late and later and later and so we just
just repossessed the whole thing in other hours and they're now, they rethought the model
of the pet. We'll just buy them, we'll install them for no cost and then we'll take the risk.
We're betting that in five years it's going to be alive.
If you look at that picture in the back in 1920, I mean all more cars.
That same street in 1900, I don't know how many more cars would be out of that street, probably more
because we're thinking that that change is going to happen a lot faster.
It's sort of a chicken and they don't feel.
People think, oh, that's a car that would be nice, but we're going to charge it.
People don't want it to install charging infrastructure because that's really expensive
and they don't see the device, the driver will let you cars.
Why would you build a bridge across that river that was crossing the river?
So the customer, when they get their electric, they pay your company for the electric.
Just like we would pay the gas company for a truck.
And then the city.
We'd have a meter on it, just like if you got it from your house, so we would sell it.
them that electricity, you know, at our rates and what way we had to, you know, so then we
would make that revenue off of it.
Yeah, it would be extra of it for the utility.
Sure.
Then we would encourage people to buy electric vehicles.
The state of Oklahoma is getting behind this as well.
The state of Oklahoma has instituted, which is a sign, I think, recently, the governor
on their sign of bill that extends the tax credit for people buying electric vehicles.
So there's a federal tax credit, the state tax credit, so the push is for electric vehicles.
You said you had written a grant hub that you said 55 was the proposed number of
towns or communities.
Yeah, that was in our grant.
And then how many did you get 26?
And how many of those have actually jumped on board with you in doing this?
Oh, they've all signed up.
They've all signed the letter of a ten.
I mean, sounds like no risk.
I can't understand why the quick trips in Tulsa which are everywhere.
Have it come on board with at least one charging station.
Well, indirectly heard from somebody on our staff who goes to church with a retired member.
Executive, quick trip.
And he says that they're planning on coming out with their own in ten years.
And we approach them.
And one man, so we got some of what we don't feel threatened by that technology.
Well, I can see what they were going to feel threatened in the short run, but in the long run.
I mean, we don't have to feel threatened by technology.
And they also, I mean, if you look at the loud as their stores, if they're going to do this, they're going to have to change it.
You can't, you're not going to have electric charge stations out front.
That people are anticipating only being at five minutes unless the technology changes dramatically.
Oh, yeah, well, the 400 kilowatt charge you can get now.
I'm not sure, but that's the max.
But the technology of the charger plus the technology in the car itself,
the car itself will limit how much electricity can, because the batteries get warm as you charge them.
And at some point they kind of have to dial that back so they don't get too warm.
But that technology is all being worked out right now, the fastest you can charge to the
vehicle that you can drive now is like 15-20 minutes.
But that'll happen, you know, when they figure out battery technology, battery technology
is increasing every year, the cost of coming down 10-20 percent every year on that.
That's getting better.
There's some day it's going to leave over.
It's going to turn into capacitors, which will be able to get a charge.
You know, that's faster faster than you can fill up the gas net.
Once they perfected that, torque packs on the old mine for somebody, especially if they get
the trucks that can be charged as well, because there's thousands of go up and down.
Which I think will lead to the mechanic end of it, too.
So I'm excited about this.
I'd like to see it.
I was filling up with gas last night, and I don't know who tuned up the guys truck.
We've got to choke me to death, trying to get the gas in my car.
So from an environmental standpoint, I think it's going to be a good thing.
Then you have not looked at this, except for the default laws.
Right.
Torgin, one of the his closely examined it.
The other question that I'd just feel compelled to fill you in on, we have not confirmed that the
turnpike authority and or the tourism and that's through tourism to the turnpike authority
that we're running where we have positions of the kick.
Now, the folks from Francis are telling us that they are being approved across the state by those entities.
The weed are not aware of it at this point for this specific thing.
I have supplied a letter that we got from the OTA.
It was a two human being in certain type of things saying that there is four charging facilities at their properties.
Do we have a legal capacity to enter into this lease for the turnpike spots?
Well, in general, no, but it's our electricity that they're going to be selling there.
That's why I'm pointing this out.
The turnpike authority has to approve it because they are the owners of the land.
And then we have possession of it through the Department of Tourism.
who has a contract with the turn by authority for which allows us to have that property.
So if we sign, if we voted the proof this tonight, is it incumbent on us then to go to the Department of Tourism
or some incumbent on Francis to go and follow up to make sure they get the approval they need?
I think it's on them, although we are, my impression is that we're jointly working on this to get the approval since the project is a whole, is mutually beneficial to both the city and to Francis.
We would be working very hard.
But you understand that just because we approve it tonight doesn't mean that it's approved from the other, the ownership of the land perspective.
Okay. So we're kind of approving it contingent on further approval by whoever.
So if we approve it and then the OTA does not approve it, are we still bound to put the one behind the on A Street?
I believe so, yes.
If we think it's a good thing, if we think it's a good thing and we lose one of them, we still, you know, from my point of view, we should have the other.
And I think, you know, there are larger cities, I brought this up last time.
They are starting to see some revenue being made off of these machines.
I mean, there's even talk, still are an admin, being on the Mesa Board.
They're actually looking at changing their rates for this equipment, because though you can probably relate to this,
because they have to build the infrastructure to get the power to them, which is, you know, I mean, a 400, you know,
who's talking about would take a pretty good infrastructure. I mean, and so then, you know, there could be a draw on it, all of a sudden, or there could set there for two days of being a draw on it.
So these cities are figuring out, okay, we'll discharge, we'll have an EV charging station rate, you know, to recoup our infrastructure.
I mean, they're, they're becoming more and more popular.
It reminds me of these emergency lights up here.
It's got a DC to DC converter in it, and they will, you know, they don't come on until you lose your power.
So there's a trick of charge that happens, and I can see even if this becomes popular, maybe we would move it from where it's at.
If I had a restaurant in town, and I had a charging station there, and somebody's going to wait for 30 minutes to get through vehicle charged,
and they're hungry or they're going to use the bathroom or whatever.
You know, it's a drawing card force.
So, terrorism just clarifies something that you said a minute ago.
The infrastructure that's going to be necessary out of the turn pie to supply 400 whatever
these things are, volts or whatever, the cost to get that power there is borne by it.
It would be borne by it.
But you have to think that infrastructure is already there, but you're looking at more of like
the use of that infrastructure.
So, the power going through that power line, you know, because there's think about it,
like we have a demand charge on commercial industrial meters.
So, I mean, you know, we charge you based on, you know, your highest use is that you have.
Well, these cities are, you know, they're just, they're just building them on the highest use
use possible that they could have because, yes, you have the infrastructure there, but you were,
the life cycle cost analysis of this infrastructure is being less and less just because of
the use of it.
We're not going to have to add it for sure.
No, sir, no, sir.
We've already got everything.
Yes, man.
I mean, I mean, either, like, when I said by mistake, the Coleman, like, but instead of the chapters,
you know, we have all that electric underground there, we went here a few years ago and put
all the electric underground.
So, we already have the transformers there and everything, you know, we would just have them
hook right up to the transformer, we would be right there.
So, we don't have to do any other infrastructure for ourselves.
So, if there's any cost to the city, it would be minimum.
Yes.
So, based on being, is it, if it's laying idle, if it's using it or, I mean, just that.
Well, just, here's the lines already running underground.
Well, they may have to date a whole, we may have to hold it in the tap into it, right?
It's already there.
Yeah.
We already have this.
We have a massive, they're huge.
Yeah.
We have like a 300 KVA transformer set in there, for example, behind chapters.
So, you know, like, yes, if this gets used a lot and that transformer gets, you know, we
can see it's getting warmer, then we'll put a 500 there or something, but I mean, that's
good for us, but that's a lot of power.
That's a lot more power.
Yeah, we're selling more power.
But we're not going to have to lay any more power.
No, sir.
Okay.
For anything.
To accommodate.
No, sir.
Okay.
Again, you know, if somebody was going to build something out there that you need to get power to
you would charge them to do that, right?
That's, that's what we intend to make this no cost.
Okay.
And if we put one on A Street, that one, in fact, anybody's electricity, there's also on
that transformer.
No, man.
So, if, if for some reason they had a large use on it, we would just put a bigger transformer in.
So, you know, like, I mean, just transformers are size for usage and how many amps you can run
off of it.
So, if, if for some reason, they had a large draw from now on, then we would just put a bigger
transformer.
And that makes me very happy because then we have, you know, you know, we have a net.
So, I don't know, I don't know what the paper is, I guess they're for me.
I'm just wondering if I was a local business owner on that block and I'm seven cars pulling, of course, right now
Cars aren't so much electric
Would I want parking spots behind mind a lot that can't I guess they can be utilized by anybody, right?
But if a car is parked there for
15-20 minutes to get charged
I don't know. I'm just trying to think of what the people on that block. I was a business
How would I feel about
Have we talked about these businesses on that block Tyler?
No, man, that's not that I'm aware of and I'd be happy to go talk to chapters and all of them
I'm just doing it to let them know what's going on and I mean, I think it would be a good draw for their business
Yeah, I don't know. I say that long term, but right now
Because there aren't that many cars that are out there. They're how far super sweet for the next door next door
Yeah, I'd have me a sign right after next to get the
Do we have any cars transformers behind the Coleman? Yes, there's transomers down through there everywhere
And I figured whatever spots
You know that two that we figured out for them. We would just somewhere try to put them close by the transomers
So I don't know I've ever seen electric car even in town, but aren't they dual fuel?
Some gasoline and then and then you charge the battery and
Yeah, I'll plug in hybrid. We have hybrid. Yeah, we have do they have
Solar panels on them as well. Not yet
GRDA just recently purchased I believe it's a vote and it's it's I got to ride in and it will set you back whenever they step on the gas
So it's very interesting when you're thinking about a combustion engine versus you know electric vehicle
The electric vehicles are gonna have that being cheaper
There's like 12 moving parts of the dry train
Christan you see new modality issues with this at all. I know did George and say anything has she
That both sides have reached out to
So the energy show there
So if we approve this, and for some reason, the term by authority says no, the city has no liability in that.
This is currently drawn. Is that correct?
Or is that the question that I was kind of clarify with Chris by text message here?
Like I said, I have not examined the contract in detail, and I'm just wanting to make sure that we are not representing that we are the owners that have property.
Everybody understands that, but I certainly don't want the contract to be saying that we are the owners of the pick property.
Prevent contingent upon OTA approval.
You would be happy with the contingent upon type clause in that.
I'm just confident that we can get a response from the OTA.
So if the motion was made to approve the lease agreement contingent on either the term by authority or the tourism authority,
whichever has the final say so over the property, you would be satisfied with that,
and then would you move forward with what is possible and make sure you got approval?
And if we're going to do that, I would suggest that the statute to the approval of both because both are involved in this and in our specific arrangement with the tick.
Okay. Any other questions?
As much as I like the concept and I like the idea, I fully, in favor of this type of thing, the way for false appeals,
I feel like we should personally speak with the businesses and get their insight on that are on that street.
So if we approve this as it's written right now that is all that vague on the downtown location,
we would have the flexibility to say to you and I'm going to use chapters, just for shortness.
I didn't see any go behind chapters or go behind the cold.
Do you have any concerns with a go behind the cold?
We just need to speak.
We're going to go.
We're going to talk with you.
I got to work with the call of him.
I love him.
I'm going to show you the word I can certain where to that.
I understand.
I'm just trying to figure out if we have a consensus tonight or not.
If his concerns could be addressed about the business owners.
And I'm happy to talk to the business owners tomorrow or Thursday or
some of my staff down there just to say we're at these two location with
you feel better and I can shoot any amount to everybody. I'm gonna just let them know.
Thank you. What are your?
It just sounds too good. I mean it doesn't. That scares me.
This goes away. And I say other companies are charging.
I know, but that's my question. Why are you picking line up loan to come in and give
us millions of dollars of things that other people are charging us for?
Because we can get the tax credits here.
Are they getting it?
Different states, different rules.
I believe a lot of it has to do with the location to being in our 44.
Well be it on an or state.
I mean they're building an infrastructure for us.
What work to buy in our base week state line to state line?
It makes sense that we're in there somewhere.
Oh yeah, it's a long thing.
This is ideal spire for this because it's like, you know, it's where
Route 66 come into a home on 44.
I'm not sure exactly what the statistic is.
But a very large percentage of the traffic that comes through a home
that comes right down the highway.
So it's the first response for it.
And you know, in five or 10 years, you know, all the store owners are going to be
wanting to say, I want to buy one from my parking lot.
Because my competitors got one, and now everything goes there.
I come to my store anymore.
So we've discussed an approval contingent on the approval of the term
like authority and the tourism authority.
And then you're concerned about the following business owners.
Are you suggesting that you want to wait and not vote until half of that,
or if I'll continue on some feedback from them?
I mean, it's kind of hard to vote if it takes on feedback,
and then it's really how varied it might be.
Some of them I just guess.
Well, and I'm going to assume that would be on board with this.
I think it's clear that I'm comfortable with it, but we need three votes,
and Brian is not here, so if you're not comfortable voting tonight,
and we've got to figure out if it is or not.
If she's not, then we've got to wait till we'll fix it.
It's just so I go.
Who knows our next meeting.
Two weeks.
Take my chance.
I mean it's good for our economy.
I mean it's good for the economy. It's good for our ecosystem. It's good for our okay.
I'm thinking.
Bill boards my shop.
I am.
I'm not.
I'm not saying okay.
If it doesn't go right there to that.
Right.
They can still see.
That part of it.
I'm real comfortable with that.
Would you, do you guys feel better there?
I mean, behind chapters.
Or do you, I mean, look at more behind the
Coleman because either one will work as far as our infrastructure.
I say the Coleman is, I mean, that.
I want them to be successful.
Yeah.
I want to get used.
And I don't know if they should have partnered with full of most of the time.
Yeah.
That's why I like the Coleman.
Full of salt.
Personally, that's what I like.
But.
So like, I mean, I think you've spoken on this last
year.
20 years down there.
You guys are going to maintain this equipment.
Oh, absolutely.
Great.
All right.
No cost.
Oh, that's.
We'll take care of all that.
There's.
They're all network.
It costs.
I was told $5,000.
You're just to keep it.
That work.
It's not.
That's when they really start making.
Right.
In the first five years.
They're not going to make.
It's.
Yeah.
Six.
Three.
Fifty.
Yeah.
Roll out.
Okay.
So.
I'm going to make a motion.
I'll take away what we talked about.
I'll tell you if I'm right around.
I'm going to make a motion to accept the parking space.
The least agreement with Francis E.V.C.
LLC contingent on approval of the turn by authority and the tourism authority.
So that's the name of it.
Do we have a second?
Second.
Roll.
Should.
What's the list?
Yes.
Forget.
Okay.
Thank you for your time.
And your.
The diligence and explaining everything.
Happy to hear.
I'm 20.
Automatically contract with the Welfare Department Chief.
We talked into the agreement with the Welfare Department on the
log making agreement.
We currently respond upon request as they do for us.
We utilize a law on district runs on what we're finding.
Road west.
So that puts us about seven miles out of them.
So with grass fires, unstructured fires, or barracks, or a good benefit to us.
So we'd like to just end.
And us to then we've been over there a couple times on the commercial fires.
Okay.
Do you like that?
So we've heard a little bit of that.
Have that we've done this before.
We do the football.
Like we can do with both.
And eventually I'd like to have everybody in our district have one with them.
Everybody surrounding us.
All right.
Makes sense.
Any concerns at all?
Is there any drawback chief to doing this?
Did you know?
Just to win.
Can we?
Rather than get there and then decide to need somebody.
If they're headed that way, you can always turn back.
And then you need to be on that weight five minutes or ten for some else.
Five minutes could make a big difference in some cases.
And it's still the longest.
The same 911 call center.
And it just depends.
Who ever did dispatch tells who to go?
Okay.
Do we have a most you've proven about 20?
I'll make a motion.
Second.
Roll call please.
Loose.
Aye.
OK.
All right.
I've been out of the 21.
Is a transfer in ownership of an old rescue truck to Welch?
Yes.
Are our old five that we replace after being came and roomed in it?
No.
It goes on the third five in that truck or room for five runs a day.
And that one, we just have got all the use out of it that we can get.
And it's Welch, heard that we were looking to surplus that they were interested.
Does it have a pump or anything on it?
No.
It's just a rescue truck.
Which they've got?
There's some tankers and grass trucks, but they don't have one truck.
They've all heard with an arm.
The rescue, whether it's farm, it's limited, you know, vehicle rescue.
They have to run a grass truck or something.
So, OK.
This will benefit them.
But it'd be like having a cat-like for them to show us that one.
They've got the canings over there that are already talking about.
If they were able to re-do them in and they need some marks.
Well, I'm glad we can help them.
Any concerns?
We have a motion to approve the transfer of ownership.
And I'm sorry, Robert.
The end there's no issues with this, right?
I mean, this is the power thing here.
We've got a Medicaid contract that re-emlies our quick pro-corporate or a loss consideration.
OK.
Thank you.
Ron, may the motion do we have a second?
Low call please.
All right.
Question.
I choose.
I don't point to those concerns.
It's a couple of my nominations to, I think, both of the year for board.
One is a re-appointment.
Renewal and the other is pointing Ron.
Penning to replace the other.
I think Ron was on the year for years ago.
It seems like I know he's.
I think he was for some reason.
I could be mistaken.
But anyway, if you for your consideration,
we'll see in there are those two nominations.
I like a motion.
Yeah, the second.
I'll second.
Roll call please.
Loose.
I forget.
All right.
Thank you.
And you visit other new business and the other new business, any one, 24 staff reports.
They're present at the other questions.
25 is a mental council announcement,
and the announcements.
26 says communications.
I think it's.
Yes, sir.
Thank you.
Thank you, sir.
So I would just like to say thank you to the City of Clarence,
to Telequip Public Works Authority,
and also to GRDA for the Future Light Help.
You know, when we had our big, the tornado, the F1 tornado,
they came through.
I was on the phone with Telequip Public Works Director.
If 330 in the morning, like saying,
can you send us some help?
Could we need some help in different areas?
You know, you sent us back to no problem.
Same thing with Clarence, seven o'clock.
I reached out to them.
They happily sent four people.
Telequip wasn't seven.
And then GRDA came down with one big crew of 69 people.
So they, I mean with them and other help,
I mean, it was definitely a blessing to get everybody back on,
and all the polls.
But back, they will have blown over from the winds and everything.
So I just want to say thank you to them.
We appreciate it.
And we appreciate it.
It doesn't work.
Hard work of all the City staff electrical and everybody.
We'll necessarily have to clean that.
But they got it down.
They got it done quickly.
Okay.
I didn't 21.
We're going to continue to meeting in the meeting room one
for an executive session.
So you'll grab your stuff.
If we're just going to adjourn from there.